hi tyler stallman whether you're just
getting started with final cut pro or
you've been using it for years
this video will have at least one tip
and or trick that you're going to start
using
every single day and thanks to
squarespace for sponsoring this video
the best place to host your portfolio
online
and let's start at the very beginning by
creating a new library
once again i'm going to be using footage
we shot for northwater in
the fall and typically i name my library
the same thing is a folder that i
put it inside and everything else and
now this brings us to our first tip
which is something that's good to figure
out early on when you're using final cut
is
when do you want to create a new library
versus adding to an existing one
and i think part of this confusion comes
from the language that final cut uses so
inside of our library we will create
projects and give my project the exact
same name
the word library implies that it's going
to hold on to a lot of different
projects like
a library but that can get pretty messy
in final cut so i would keep the
projects inside of your library all
related so they're all sharing footage
maybe they're all part of the same
shoot but more or less i have one
library per project
next i'll show you how i do my file and
folder structure so i did already edit
this video so there is a file structure
existing right here
and i will have a folder for videos
images audio
and inside of video there can be
different either shoot days or
cameras depending on exactly what i'm
doing i like to try to keep it very
loosely organized i know some people use
events as the primary way of organizing
footage within final cut but i find
keywords
way more useful so here i'm going to
import everything
i am going to leave files in place
because i don't like final cut
managing my files more about that in a
minute
but what i'm going to do is import the
audio images and video
and i'm going to select keywords from
folders this is going to take
the title of each folder and use it as a
keyword
so now all of our footage is in the
library and if we open up our event here
you can see that there are a series of
keywords so now our event can be
anything i often don't rename them but i
don't know we can just
name the same things the project if we
want more importantly we're now able to
really
find things so we had two days of
shooting for this commercial and we used
two different cameras so the gimbal
shots are shot on the eos r
so i'm gonna make the browser a little
bit bigger here and select a1
and day two and then just by the file
name i can tell these are all
of the eos r videos select them all
command k to open up keywords and i'm
just going to call this canon r
then with those days still selected i'm
going to go down and i can tell again by
the file name these are all the c200
files
and you can add as many keywords as you
want but i'd strongly recommend
only add the amount that are actually
useful to you so for example with
cameras
these have different log profiles on
them so i have to color grade them
differently
so if i select all of my c200 footage
this was shot in canon log2 so if i go
into info i can select
the custom c log 2 profile that i made
which you can download below it's based
on alexa luts and
it looks great it's my favorite lut that
i've got
and now all the shots are in beautiful
rec 709 full
contrast so they look good again
i've also got one that i use for c log c
log 3 and most importantly a film
emulation that i put on virtually every
single project
including this one right now so if you
want to download my luts link is in the
description below
i'm actually going to take a little step
back select the library click modify
settings and let's take a look at where
we're storing things so
right now the media is set to be stored
inside of the library
if you're storing it in the library
that's how apple tries to make it easier
for you i really prefer to choose
the video folder and keep it all in
there it makes it easier to move
files around and nothing i always do
this caused huge problems for me it's
actually part of the reason i switched
to premiere for a few years
until i figured this out final cut can
start to take up
your whole hard drive if you let it one
way to prevent it is to change your
cache location from
inside of the library to the root folder
of the
main project and i put it right there so
it is visible to me
the reason for this is now it is just
it's completely visible if i click on it
i can see
right now it's 27 megabytes that's
nothing by the end of editing this it
will be hundreds of gigabytes it will be
enormous
and you can just delete it when you're
done you don't actually need to keep the
cache file around you can actually just
delete it as you're editing
so whenever i need to clear up hard
drive space i look at completed projects
and just delete all those cache files
from the finder the other big thing is
that when you are importing your files
make sure that you
have a close look at where your files
are being copied to because if you click
copy as opposed to leave in place it'll
create duplicates
of all of your videos same thing goes
for create optimized media
and i mean kind of create proxies just
make sure that you're watching those
because you don't want to end up having
multiple versions of all the same videos
because you can fill a whole hard drive
in just a few minutes
so to be clear i never create optimized
and i do create proxy media
if i'm working with files that slow my
computer down like the r5
r6 a7s3 all these new cameras really can
slow down editing all right in this next
tip
i learned from a friend that does really
high-end commercial work for like
mercedes-benz and game of thrones and
like all
the big stuff thomas grove carter has
great tutorials of his own
but the first thing i do when i'm
sorting b-roll style footage which this
isn't narrative none of this stuff
connects but i'm gonna go through
everything and like well i should go to
the start and i want to watch
every single clip so you're just kind of
checking out what you have and as you
see
good moments you press i and then when
the good part's over you press o and now
you set in in and out so if we look over
here there is a
yellow section that is selected now your
first instinct might be to
drag this down to the timeline or press
the e key and that drops into the
timeline
don't drop it in the timeline yet the
much more useful thing to do
is press the f key now this favorites it
you can see that there is a
small green line above it here and
you're going to go through watching all
your clips actually i see she's got an
elastic on her wrist there we got that
off
here okay so yeah let's use these ones
another favorite and you can just really
quickly the big goal here is just to
like remove
all of the junk so i'm going to press i
and
oh in that general section this whole
take is junk so i'm going to select it
and press delete
it works better for you sometimes i use
the mouse and just select the good part
like this
good old-fashioned click and drag oh and
this kid he ruined the shot
and you're gonna go through and watch
every single shot that you took
and select your favorite parts of it now
why are we doing this because at the end
instead of viewing all clips you can
just view favorites and these are
just the sections that we decided are
the best and this can take a few hours
so i'm just going to quickly show you
this is what it looks like on the
completed project so you end up with a
lot like
favorite everything you think you might
possibly use
so you have a lot of clips to choose
from anything that doesn't get favorited
might get lost in the future and
probably won't end up in your final edit
and then a beautiful thing if you shot
things in sequence which i don't know we
kind of did here like this is all just
b-roll so there's no real sequence but
if i select everything that is related
here in the favorites
and i drag them down into the timeline i
like i basically just have
a watchable video now it's like it's
it's edited i mean
kind of like this is not the final thing
so we're gonna have to delete a lot of
this
and the reason for all this is it's
scalable and non-destructive so you can
always go back and find
alternate versions that you liked you're
not like losing stuff which
can happen if you add it straight to the
timeline it's very hard to go back
and find another version of a take that
you might have liked
if you want to know more from thomas
grove carter he's been on the podcast a
few times and he
is a damn genius when it comes to final
cut pro so
check out those episodes and check out
his tutorials too great guy that
technique of
favoriting everything is really great
for b-roll or if your shots are broken
up a lot when i do videos
like this that i'm recording right now
it's one long take of a-roll
and then i cut that up so i'm gonna open
up a new project so in this one i was
breaking down my
c200 rig and i treat this very
differently so what i do here is i drop
the whole thing
on the timeline here is you know
beginning to end all the bloopers and
everything in between
and then instead of just starting to cut
the important step is first
i press option g and create a new
compound clip and this can just be
called
a roll clip whatever like totally
doesn't matter what it is the point is
now
when you start editing so i put some you
know random
cuts in here chop it up delete something
if i double click and go inside
the compound clip everything is still
there and i can make changes that are
now affected all the way through so for
example this has absolutely no color in
it if i add the saturation
back into the log it is all the way
through that whole thing and this
is so helpful for long clips if you're
trying to keep a whole bunch of stuff in
sync
that was shot at the exact same time
it's way easier when it's inside a
compound clip and this is how i edit
things this might be
super basic if you've been editing for a
while but if you haven't seen this yet
it'll
change everything for you okay i'm not
doing this for real so it doesn't really
matter what i'm saying here i'm just
going to go through and okay
i know that this is a first take and
what you might do the most basic thing
is to select the blade tool with b cut
then you'd go back to select tool click
that and delete it
that's one way to remove things now the
thing that you should start doing and
hopefully you already have been is you
go to the part of the timeline where you
want the clip to start
and you press option left square bracket
and it will
trim a ripple trim everything before
that point
so then at the end of my take i will
press command
b for the blade tool it'll just cut
things and then i go to the beginning of
the next take i can tell those are false
starts uh
i think this is the real one over here
and i press option
left square bracket and it will trim
everything to the left
now i could also do that in the other
direction i could go to the beginning
the next take over here press command
b and then from here when i start
looking at my phone
i could press option and right square
bracket and it will trim everything to
the right
this is essential to being fast in final
cut pro if you are not editing this way
you are probably editing much more
slowly and to take that further i
actually go in and i customize
all of mine so if i switch over you can
see i've already saved it
and all that's doing is i've got like
trim and trim start
i assign those to just be the left and
right bracket without
any modification keys because i just use
them so much and now i'm going to jump
back into north water here i've added
those favorite clips into
a timeline and let's say i've added
everything but it's a little bit too
long
very important is to create duplicates
as you move along now something to keep
in mind is the difference between
duplicate
and snapshot project is something i just
learned i didn't actually know this
difference
if you're using compound clips duplicate
will make those compound clip changes
propagate through all of the different
versions so if i duplicate this
northwater fall 1 will have any compound
clip changes or multi-cam clip changes
whereas if i go
snapshot project now those compound
clips
live completely on their own so it
depends on how you're structuring things
snapshots are kind of the safest where
you're least likely to screw things up
but as you go along and especially when
you're making shorter edits of your
project
be sure to save them by duplicating and
snapshotting your project
as you go so you can revert back to
earlier changes and now since we were so
organized as we
created our project i've got i've got a
new tip i just figured this out recently
so as a youtuber
i create too much footage like this is
4k raw that i'm shooting in right now
and i do not want to keep all of that
but i do want to keep all of my favorite
b-roll shots so
when i'm done editing everything if it's
the kind of project where
i can throw the other stuff away not
every project is like that if you're
working for a client
make sure they know if you're supposed
to hold on to all the footage or not
but if it's that kind of project where
you get to make decisions you can go and
select all your favorite clips here
which
is actually not that much footage go to
file
and send to compressor and it will send
eight clips in this case all to
compressor
and i'm going to select all and
depending how important the project is
i'll either use
prores 422 or prores lt start batch
and now it's just going to save my
favorite moments of the most important
clips
so what i can end up archiving is a
really small folder that has everything
that i used in the edit
plus a little bit more and it's just
it's really easy to go back
and reuse those clips for future youtube
videos
but you've got to be warned this can
break your final cut project because now
these are new video files they won't
line up with the ones that you are
editing with
so there's some caveats this is just a
way to store
b-roll footage so in my case i like to
create a bit of an archive
of older clips that we've shot in
previous videos of
say products that might show up in
future videos but it's way smaller than
holding on to the all the originals and
i've got one more quick one but after
i thank squarespace for sponsoring this
video which is the best place to host
your video portfolio on the internet
of course you can upload to youtube or
vimeo or
instagram or all sorts of social
platforms but in the end you don't
really own
or control those spaces squarespace is
somewhere that you can completely design
the whole website to fit your brand
you can customize the domain name and
most importantly you have full control
forever because you own this website
their templates and design tools make it
just as easy as using a social network
to set something up that feels like
it's yours and that looks beautiful to
your audience but they won't know that
it came from a template because
you can customize it so much so easily
squarespace's seo and analytics tools
are also everything you need
to really run a professional website so
let's say you're building a store and
you are trying to sell a product
you can keep an eye on every detail of
it both of making sure that people
find you online and where they are
visiting on your site
to make sure you get conversions there
is so much you can do with squarespace
so go
check them out today at squarespace.com
and
once you've started a free trial and
built a simple website in just a few
minutes
then you go to squarespace.com tyler
stallman
and using offer code tyler stallman you
can get 10 off your first
website or domain i've been using
squarespace kind of forever
and i'm going gonna keep using it
because their sites are beautiful and
easy to use
and thanks again squarespace for
sponsoring this video so i've added some
music and voice over to this clip but in
order to hear it we're gonna have to
turn down the music now
in the olden days what i would do is
that option click to add
different points on the audio track and
then i would drag them down let's zoom
in a little
so now we've got a little fade as it's
going there's a way easier way to do
that that i didn't know about till
recently
instead i use the r key which stands for
range
i select the range of my voiceover and i
just drag down
on the audio and now i'm ducking in
exactly that spot
who knew i mean maybe you did let me
know what great tips i missed in here
because i'd love to do this video
again with all sorts of new things
thanks again for watching guys
and don't forget to check out the
podcast stallman podcast on whatever
podcast player you use
and i'll see you in the next video did i
already say that
anyway bye guys
you